Welcome back. Welcome back. It is lovely
to see all of you.
It is my great pleasure to introduce our
next RI seminar speaker, our very own
Professor Maxim Kovitz.
Um Max works on the theoretical
foundations of machine learning, but
also interactive and sequential
problems, which are
all problems in robotics.
Um
Max did his PhD
at Berkeley. Actually, that's where I
first got to know him.
Uh we took a few classes together and um
Max is a really really smart guy. One of
my most salient memories is So Max was
doing like hardcore machine learning
research.
And at Berkeley, you have to take these
oral preliminary exams. They're like
whiteboard exams on a specific topic.
You can pick to do it on machine
learning, you can pick to do it on a
control or optimization.
And you know, I did the control
optimization one. I expected We all
expected Max to do the machine learning
one, but he was like, "You know what?
I'm going to just like decide to take
the control one for once." And then he
just He ended up doing the best on that
exam and it was super embarrassing for
all of us who were like focusing on
control with THIS LIKE OTHER GUY DOING
MACHINE LEARNING WHO WAS LIKE, "YEAH,
THAT'S ACTUALLY LIKE pretty easy." So
anyways, I've always
been a great admirer of the way that
like Max thinks Max thinks abstractly
These days a lot more empirically as
well and I'm excited to learn from him
today. Thanks Andrea. Thank you.
Um
>> [applause]
>> Uh Andrea and I also became friends in
the early days of meme culture. This is
like 2016. Do you kids know who you
gander knuckles is?
>> [laughter]
>> Okay. Yeah. Yeah, I remember. Yeah.
Yeah, okay. Anyway,
uh so that's not relevant for today's
talk. So I'm going to talk to you today
about generative control.
So kind of the kind of philosophical
point of departure for today's talk is
this you know, Moravec paradox. Hans
Moravec actually who I think was here.
He was in RI. And he noted I think many
others have also noted that it's been
far more difficult to get robots to be
able to do things in the physical world
than you know, it is it has been to get
AI systems to work in symbolic domains.
Um and yet we've seen tremendous
progress in robotics. I don't know if
Tonga is here today, but this is a video
of him collecting
demonstrations of shirt folding and then
using using behavior cloning as a way to
train a robot policy to shirt fold. And
the reason that I I show this example is
because by today's standards it's
incredibly banal. So I was informed
yesterday by Nina Balkan that shirt
folding was in Peter Abbeel's job talk
and now it's infra that a master student
A very talented master student, but but
a student is is using to begin the
project rather than sell themselves in
the job market.
So kind of how did we get to this point?
Well, behavior cloning also historically
sort of began at Carnegie Mellon. Early
efforts in self-driving were using it.
And in the early 2020s it became very
popular as a modality for learning and
manipulation. But then around 2023 some
inflection point happened and it became
so successful that it was the impetus
for many companies to start scaling
models based on this as a way of
training their systems.
So what caused this inflection point?
And there's a very stupid answer, which
is this we started collecting more data.
And you might call this the pragmatic
Moravec's paradox, right? That
historically it's been harder to
instrument data collection for robotics
and now where we're at a point where we
could start doing it. But I think
there's another point that might be
missed, which is that there were certain
key algorithmic breakthroughs that took
place in this 2023 inflection point. And
these were the things that enabled us at
least at the beginning to start learning
from the data we collected even in the
initial efforts which were so much
smaller in scale.
Uh so this is the algorithmic Moravec's
paradox that robot learning is
fundamentally more challenging at least
at smaller scales until you have a
couple key algorithmic choices that
enable learning from the data that you
collect.
Um and so in this talk we're going to
try to provide some mathematical support
for what's going on in this algorithmic
formulation of Moravec's paradox. We're
going to describe why learning from
demonstration can be fundamentally more
challenging in continuous control
settings such as those encountered in
robotics as opposed to settings like
symbolic reasoning like in language. And
then we're going to try to explain how
those kind of key breakthroughs that
cause this inflection point, they
actually mitigate some of the
fundamental challenges that we
encountered in learning and control
systems.
So what are the interventions we're
going to talk about? If you do a lot of
modern robot manipulation research, you
may be familiar with these. The first is
action chunking. This is the process
where you condition on a few historical
observations and predict whole sequences
of actions in open loop rather than
having a very very high frequency
reactive policy.
Uh and this is kind of considered one of
the foundational innovations. The other
that's sometimes more visible is that of
using generative models as
parameterizations of action
distributions. Sort of under the
assumption that actions when we collect
from diverse human demonstration have
multiple modes or diversity in the in
the distribution that we collect. And
sort of it's it's suggested that
generative models are better suited for
for for modeling this kind of
distribution. Then we're going to see
that maybe there are other motivations
behind using generative models in
control at the end of the talk.
So kind of the fundamental claim that
we're going to try to make that unifies
these decisions is that modern robot
learning can be thought about as
reparameterizing the closed-loop
dynamics between robot and control
system. And that these interventions
really act on a control level. And in
fact, these reparameterizations are the
things that now put us in a regime where
the bitter lesson can take effect and
then the boring pragmatic Moravec's
paradox, we just need more data, starts
to become more salient.
So to begin I want to explain why
behavior cloning can be challenging in
robot learning.
And I'm going to do that by kind of
first introducing the behavior cloning
paradigm for those that might not be
familiar with it. So we're going to
operate in a Markov decision process.
I'm sure many of us are familiar here.
We have states, we have actions, we have
transitions between states and actions,
we have rewards, and we have an initial
distribution over initial conditions. Uh
we also have a problem horizon. That's
the number of steps that the actor, for
example our robot, might take. And the
problem horizon will become really
important in today's talk.
So the key object is a policy. It's just
a way of describing what your agent
does. It's a mapping from states to the
distributions over actions.
Uh and that can be either describe what
your robot is doing, but also policies
have been used to formalize language
models. For example, a language model
can be thought of as a policy which
takes in a context of tokens and spits
out another token as its actions. And
the dynamics are just concatenation to
the context.
So what are we trying to do? Well, we're
trying to maximize reward, at least for
today. So the we'll define the reward of
a policy is just the expectation of its
cumulative reward. Where that
expectation happens by drawing initial
conditions, then choosing actions
according to our policy, and finally
transitioning according to the
transition dynamics of our MDP.
And so offline, before I describe
behavior cloning, I want to describe the
protocol, which is sort of like the
world in which behavior cloning exists.
So what we're going to do is we're going
to assume that the expert, our human,
collects data and gives that data to the
robot, right? So that data can be
sequences of trajectories consisting of
states and actions. For the roboticists
in the room, which are many of you, we
know we don't actually get state, we get
observation. But today we're going to
focus on state because if things are
challenging in state-based control, nine
times out of 10, not always 10 times out
of 10, they're they're challenging in
image-based. Turns out sometimes
image-based can be easier for weird
reasons. But uh we'll work on
state-based control today. And so we're
going to give those trajectories to an
imitator and the imitator is going to do
some algorithm, which we'll describe,
which is going to try to return some new
policy that has the following property.
The property should be that that
the cumulative reward of that policy, J
of pi hat, should only be a little bit
less than the cumulative reward of what
our expert gets. So smaller than some
number epsilon and here epsilon is just
getting smaller and smaller as I collect
more data, right? That's what we would
like to have happen.
Now, how can we achieve this? Well,
behavior cloning is one algorithm that
abides by the protocol of learning from
an expert. So in behavior cloning, you
just use supervised learning to train
your policy. So more specifically, what
you'll do is you'll take all your expert
data.
You'll specify some loss function that's
related to how you describe your policy.
And then you'll try to find the policy
which minimizes this loss on the data
that you have, for example by doing
gradient descent on some architecture of
neural networks.
And um
the reason we do this is because there's
lots of reasons why we want to do
supervised learning. It's an algorithm
that's very easy to learn.
It's empirically works very very well,
right? Like image classification, these
sorts of things. And theoretically it
also is nice. We have very strong strong
history of generalization error
guarantees that say that if I minimize
this loss on my expert data, then the
thing that minimizes it will be close to
the expert, the global minimizer under
certain conditions.
But the problem is this is just because
we can minimize the supervised learning
error does not a priori imply that we're
going to get small reward. And the I
think the best way to see this is is
through visualizing it. So by minimizing
supervised error, we're doing it under
the distribution of our states that our
expert visits, right? So at every state
that we see, we're trying to find an
action that's close to what the expert
would have done anchored at that state.
But of course, when we deploy the
policy, we're taking actions from the
states that we reach. And these actions
can cause errors which add up over time,
often leading to what's called the curse
of horizon where errors grow as the
horizon grows.
So this is the fundamental challenge.
So how bad is this curse of horizon?
Well, let's start by considering the
case where we're doing like a discrete
task like symbolic reasoning in
language. And we'll consider a very
special case of the zero-one loss. So
this is a loss that gives you a penalty
of one if you get the wrong action.
Let's say you predict the wrong token
and zero otherwise. Now in modern
language modeling actually we use the
log loss, we use cross entropy. It
actually turns out this works even
better than the zero-one loss and I'm
not going to go into that that that
research today. But we'll focus on the
zero-one loss for now.
So what you can show, actually this is
an old result due to Drew Bagnell who is
I think still affiliated with CMU,
is that the compounding error effect,
the suboptimality that you get in terms
of your reward, is at most horizon
factor times the suboptimality that you
get in your behavior cloning loss. So
essentially we do have some curse of
horizon, but it's relatively mild. It's
at most linear in how long the problem
takes. And the intuition for this is
that if you have a zero-one loss, you
either make a mistake or you don't. And
so at every time step there's some
probability of making a mistake and
those probabilities accumulate according
to the length of the horizon, but
otherwise you don't make a mistake and
you do perfectly and do exactly what the
expert would do. So it's not so bad in
this case in the discrete setting.
But, now we're going to work in control
systems. So, in a control system, we'll
work on a special kind of MDP where we
have continuous states and continuous
actions. So, we're in the continuous
world. Uh transition dynamics will be
given by deterministic dynamical system
denoted by F. And again, we have
rewards, initial state distributions.
And in particular, kind of the salient
thing is now our states and actions are
continuous valued. And we'll see why
that's a problem.
So, for today's talk, because we want to
prove negative results at least to
start, we're going to work in the
simplest setting where the dynamics are
deterministic and the policy optimal
policy are smooth. So, smooth just means
that they have derivatives and those
derivatives are kind of continuous.
So, let's do behavior cloning in this
setting.
Now, the problem is this. If we assume
that we're in continuous state action
spaces, we can't learn in the 0-1 loss
or the log loss. The reason being that
we'll always make some irreducible
amount of error, right? We can always
try to get closer and closer to the
perfect action, but we might not get
that exactly correct.
So, instead what we'll do is we'll just
work on learning in the square loss,
which is historically how behavior
cloning had been conducted up until the
recent revolution in generative control
policies. And the reason we do this is
because, well, this is something that at
least is learnable. There's sort of um
very strong empirical evidence and sort
of rich theoretical evidence suggesting
that learning in the square loss isn't
so bad.
So, what we're going to ask is if I can
learn in the square loss, is it possible
for me to do behavior cloning without
this without significant compounding
error?
So, let me convince you that this is
actually hard.
And in order to do so, I need to
convince you that this is hard even in a
regime that seems like it's very easy
and seems like it should be really nice.
So, let me describe that regime to you.
The learner is given a set of possible
worlds, and in each possible world,
there's an expert pi and a dynamics,
right? So, the the policy is tailored
for the dynamics.
In addition, uh for every pair of these,
all the policies are smooth, they're
deterministic, they're Markovian, just
meaning that the policies depend only on
the current state.
And finally, they're stable.
Now, stable is a control theoretic
condition that we'll describe a little
bit more in detail after we go through
the result, but informally, you can
think of stability as saying that if you
make a mistake, you forget it really
fast. So, the thing to visualize is a
pendulum that has a little bit of
friction. If I perturb it, eventually
the oscillations will relax back to the
equilibrium point, and you should keep
that in mind when you hear the word
stability.
So, the last thing we're going to assume
is that the learner is promised that the
true policy and the true dynamics, they
lie in the set of possible worlds that
they know.
So, they'll be able to represent this.
Right. So, we can think of these
conditions 1 through 3 as specifying one
of the nicest possible behavior cloning
instances. Ones where it's easy to
learn, we know what we need to learn,
and we shouldn't have this we shouldn't
have very strong sensitivity if we make
mistakes given by the stability
condition.
We're going to now impose a fourth
condition,
which is just going to say that the
learner can't return policies that are
much more sophisticated than what the
expert is doing.
And later on, we'll see how removing
this condition actually enables behavior
cloning.
So, formally, we remember that we assume
that this expert is Markovian, only
depending on the current state, and is
smooth and deterministic. And
essentially, for this result, we'll
assume that the that the learner has to
be the same. The learner cannot be much
more general than the expert.
So, now let's state the result.
The result says this. You give me your
favorite scaling law, so n to the minus
alpha. This is how much error should
decrease as I get more data.
And I'm going to give you a set of
problems that satisfy all the nice
conditions on the last slide that have
the following two properties.
So, the first property is that the
supervised learning on the square loss
obeys the scaling law that you gave me,
right? It's going to the error is going
to go down in terms of the data I
collect on the expert distribution at
this rate. You can make alpha 0.1, you
can make alpha a million. I can give you
an instance that has this property.
However, any algorithm that satisfies
the restrictions we placed in condition
4 is going to pay for that rate times 2
to the horizon, right? Times an
exponential factor in how long it takes
to complete the task.
So, what this is showing is that error
is compounding even in this nicest
possible case by an exponential factor
in the problem horizon.
It's growing very large.
Now, you might say, "Well, what if I
just don't do behavior cloning? Maybe
there's a better algorithm that I can
design." Turns out this result will
still apply. Behave It applies to any
algorithm that satisfies the restriction
4, that has policies that are the same
as the expert.
And then you might say, "Well, what if I
use reward? For example, offline
reinforcement learning can be really
powerful. Can that help?" No. So, this
result applies even if I know the ground
truth reward function, which means that
all algorithms include offline RL
algorithms because they would use the
reward. So, none of these are are going
to overcome the bound.
So, essentially, we I'm billing this as
the quantitative Moravec paradox in the
sense that it establishes that you have
this exponential in horizon effect if
you're trying to do behavior cloning in
the continuous world, whereas we only
had a linear effect when we tried to see
what was going on in the discrete world,
So, now I'm going to try to explain why
this happens. And from seeing why this
happens, we'll then be able to
understand why some of the more modern
interventions in robot learning have
been as successful as they've been.
So, robot learning is a control problem,
right? We have actions, we have
dynamics, we have states or
observations, we have policies.
But, what makes a control problem? It's
just a problem that has dynamics, but
typically, at least culturally, it sort
of it has this idea of stability.
And stability is informally the
sensitivity of a system to perturbations
of its inputs. So, in the world of
control, that's really what we care
about. So, for example, the upside down
pendulum is stable. It doesn't have too
much sensitivity. The uh the inverted
pendulum is unstable. Any small push can
cause it to topple over to one side or
another side.
So,
what we'll do is is
One thing to note is that stability is
very naturally related to compounding
error, right? If you have high
sensitivity to to mistakes, then of
course, small errors you make will will
blow up. But of course, we've assumed
that the system is stable.
So, what does that mean?
We're going to use a definition of
stability called incremental stability
due to Agrichef.
And incremental stability, it basically
says the following. Imagine I start at
the same initial state S. And now I take
two sequences of actions starting at S.
How different are the two states that I
end up at? And what this equation says
is that the difference between these two
states is scales like the difference in
the actions, but the contribution of
actions in the past decays if this
parameter rho is strictly less than 1,
which we'll assume that it is. So,
basically, in a stable system, if I make
a mistake sometime in the past, its
contribution to my current error will
will will be exponentially small in how
far in the past it was,
So, naively, this is the kind of
condition that we really want. This is a
condition that should prevent
exponential compounding error rather
than be consistent with it.
So, let's see what's going on.
So, what are we promised? Well, we're
promised that the system is open loop
stable, meaning that if we have an
adversary that perturbs actions, then
the resulting differences in states
aren't too large, and in fact, these
mistakes will decay and vanish
exponentially in how long we we've made
them in the past.
Similarly, we're promised closed loop
stability in our assumption. So, this
means that if you perturb actions given
by the expert, formally, you consider
what's called a closed loop dynamics
where you consider an dynamics acting on
states and action perturbations delta A
that add action perturbations to what
the policy would do.
And here, we're also assuming that this
is closed loop stable.
Right? So, these are the two
assumptions.
But, the fundamental problem is that
just because we're promised both of
these,
doesn't ensure that the policy that we
learn, that pi hat, is going to be
closed loop stable. In fact, it might
not
ensure this.
So, let's try to understand why this is
not possible. Uh this is a construction
that's kind of cool, but also very sad.
Uh so, essentially, you can construct
two sets of policies and dynamics that
are both open loop and closed loop
stable.
Now, in addition, they have the
following property.
Consider the subspace of the second
basis vector, so 0 1. This is in two
dimensions.
Uh you can construct it so that they all
agree on the subspace and that they all
preserve the subspace, meaning which if
meaning that if I have a state in the
subspace, all the dynamics and policies
will keep me on the subspace, right? So,
I'm over all the way over here.
So, essentially, what this means is that
from the if I just collect expert data,
I cannot distinguish if I'm in world 1
or world 2. There's not enough
information.
But, however, there's a problem,
which is that if I try to have any
policy,
sorry, this is older version. If I have
any policy that's of a certain kind
agreeing on the subspace. So, if I take
something that agrees with my expert one
pair of these dynamics.
Right? There's actually no way to
stabilize both and agree on this data.
And the problem is because these are
because [clears throat] these instances
are indistinguishable, I don't know
which one I'm I'm on. So, from a
robustness standpoint, I have to either
try to stabilize both, but I can't.
And so, what we're able to show then is
that if you make an initial mistake,
which we can use sort of the theory of
non-parametric statistics to show that
you will, just by showing that you're
sort of the magnitude of your mistakes
agree with the scaling law that we saw
in that that result,
then those mistakes are going to seed
some initial error,
and that initial error on one of these
two possible worlds, which you can't
tell apart, is going to become sort of
larger and larger due to instability
compounding the error exponentially.
And the kind of crucial observation here
is really this distance-wise error. This
is why the continuous world is
different. In the discrete world, we're
either right or we're wrong, but in the
continuous world, or we're right or
wrong with some probability, but here,
we make these like metric errors, right?
Because 0-1 learning is not possible,
and these are what seed the instability
that can really kind of mess us up.
So, in the next part of the talk, the
rest of the talk, I'm going to try to
answer what we can do about it, how we
can overcome the pathology that's
illuminated over here.
We'll begin with the first intervention.
This most directly
affects this pathology, and it's also
the one that we have strong theoretical
guarantees for.
And this is led by Thomas Eng. He's a
PhD student at UPenn. He's going to be
joining as a postdoc in my group next
year.
So, the first intervention that was
incredibly successful was this idea of
action chunking. I'll actually I
actually believe that action chunking is
perhaps more important than the
intervention on the next slide, but
potentially not necessary in the long
run.
Um so, what is action chunking doing?
Well, remember we had this restriction
on what our policies could learn, right?
We said the learner must return
Markovian policies. These are policies
that only depend on the current
observation.
But what action chunking does, this
intervention where we predict multiple
actions at the same time by by
execution, is it actually correlates
actions across time.
Because now the action I'm taking at
some point was correlated or dependent
on observation I made a couple steps
ago. So it's non-Markov. So at least
from a sanity check, it says that action
chunking policies are not covered by our
negative result.
So let me tell you what they actually
can do.
Uh just for those that haven't seen
action chunking training, the way that
you would train such a thing is for
example, if you're using regression, you
just minimize a loss to a sequence of
actions. So rather than predicting one
action, you predict a whole vector of
actions and you just minimize that.
So what we're going to do is state
action chunking in a case where the
dynamics are open state open loop
stable, like the lower bound. We'll get
to the open loop unstable setting later.
And essentially what we show is the
following. As long as your chunk length
is bigger than bigger is is is bigger
than some sort of threshold K star
sufficiently large, you have no
compounding error.
So your suboptimality and reward is at
most the behavior cloning loss at the
chunk level times some constant C.
So yes, we're avoiding compounding
error.
But also these constants K star and and
C star are polynomial and relevant
factors and they're not dependent in
horizon.
In particular, the effect saturates to
the critical K star. So it's not that
you're just cutting the horizon by some
amount, you're actually avoiding
compounding error all together. It's
sort of a phase change in the dynamics
itself.
Um so let's see what what's going on.
So recall that if you don't have any
action chunking, you're just going to
have a ton of compounding error.
But if you do have action chunking,
because your system is open loop stable,
you'll might make some mistakes, but the
mistakes won't be too large, right?
Because you have open loop stability, so
you know, you might have a little bit of
error at every time, but it'll saturate.
Now, if we want to analyze action
chunking, we can do a thought
experiment.
Imagine that I could magically reset
back to my expert state over here.
Right?
Then again, I could roll out a action
chunk that I've learned and I'd make
again some small amount of error.
So now here is kind of the magical fact
about action chunking.
Assuming that your policy is Lipschitz,
meaning that it doesn't change too
wildly as you perturb it,
uh and some other kind of other
conditions, essentially what we can show
is that the learned policy is closed
loop stable.
And what that means is that if I think
of this as a perturbation, so I think of
where I got to here as a perturbation of
the ideal trajectory that was perfectly
reset,
then that perturbation is going to not
push the trajectory starting from here
too far from this idealized one in the
pink.
Right? So that this is actually going to
kind of track this trajectory in the
following sense.
And the process can repeat of all
keeping the compounding error controlled
over the duration of the trajectory.
Now, essentially what's going on is that
the rate of contraction is overcoming
the sensitivity of your policy. So your
policy might have some decent amount of
sensitivity here. This might not be
contractive, but that if you take
multiple steps of the chunk, that's
enough time for this contraction to take
hold and overcome these mistakes that
you made.
And that's what's going on.
Now, you might actually see this. Yes,
Andrea. Quick question. Um
So a trivial action chunk is a chunk of
length
Yes.
>> what you used to be doing. Yes. So is it
any chunk of greater than length Oh, no.
It has to be It has to be greater than
this K star, which depends on the
control properties of the system. I see.
So roughly it has to be like Lipschitz
constant divided by some contractivity
and then you kind of get into Yeah. Got
it. Exactly. Yeah, of course.
Perfect. So uh you might also, if you
want some just like visual evidence, if
you've played around with action
chunking, you might see that non-action
chunk policies are super jittery and
then when you action chunk them, they're
really smooth. That's kind of you can
kind of think of this as like the
theoretical correlate of that of that
observation.
Um let's actually test this. So what I
wanted to do is test action chunking in
like a really, really simple case where
we don't have any other compounding
confounding factors. So we trained it
with a we trained a policy with
deterministic experts and state-based
regression. So there's no partial
observ- observability issues.
And essentially what we did is we looked
at different predicted action chunks. So
you might predict a long action chunk
say for representation learning
purposes, but only use a small one. And
we also looked at the performance as you
evaluate longer chunks. And indeed, it
seems that the evaluation length of the
chunk seems to be really the dominant
factor. It's not just that you need to
predict long chunks, you actually need
to evaluate long ones, which is
consistent with the picture that we have
on the previous slide.
Um so there are other hypotheses and I
think many of them are very valid about
why action chunking works,
representation learning, mitigating
partial observability,
uh but I think that sort of this this
stability interpretation, which sort of
looks a little bit like receding horizon
control, I think it's maybe the at least
is an important consideration that I
think was kind of underemphasized in
some of the literature previously.
So the core assumption that enables our
analysis of action chunking to work is
that the dynamics are open loop stable,
right? Now, why should you believe this?
Well, I think a lot of modern robotics,
especially around this 2023 inflection
point, was doing its best to put us in a
regime where this open loop stability
was true.
So a very popular thing to do, whether
you're doing joint control or end
effector control, is position tracking.
Right? So you'll predict positions that
you want your robot to get to and then
you'll use a low-level controller to
stabilize your robot around those
positions.
Right? So effectively, this is putting
you into the regime where the system, at
least the robot only system, is open
loop stable.
So what you can think of as going on is
that essentially we're just doing a
bunch of tricks to reparameterize our
system into stability.
So we're using, for example, if we just
predict raw torques at joints, this
might be unstable.
We use position or end effector control
or more generally position tracking
control to make our system stable.
But given our lower bound, our negative
result, stability alone isn't enough to
avoid compounding error. And so we let
we add in action chunking, which makes
it so that the learned policies
themselves are stable and therefore
don't have compounding error. So we can
think about all these interventions as
just building up a control stack that
provides greater stability.
Uh maybe a question, do we need action
chunking?
Um
So I think action chunking has some
downsides, right? It makes the policy
far less reactive, which might be which
might not work.
And it sort of also addresses
instability mostly related to the
embodiment, right? We cannot use
position control to stabilize the world
around us.
So kind of my vibe conjecture is that as
we move towards more embodied data and
and maybe some hierarchical planning, I
think in the long run we will be able to
get rid of action chunking. I also think
that using more like on-policy
reinforcement learning can directly
mitigate these effects. You can kind of
prove it or you can just do the
experiments,
but I I don't really think I think this
is sort of a transient intervention, but
I do think this sort of system one
system two perspective probably has more
longevity.
So finally,
is action chunking enough? Well, as we
alluded to, we can't stabilize objects,
right? There may be cases in robotics
where we're trying to manipulate or
interface with the external world and we
cannot guarantee just because we're
using certain control in a robot that
the external world will behave the way
we want it to.
So are there interventions that might do
better in stabilizing the external
world? And that's what we'll try to
conclude with.
So the final intervention we're discuss
today is generative control, the use of
generative models as control policies
uh for this end. Okay. And this was led
by Chaoyue. He's a PhD student with
Guanya Shi.
So the motivation for generative control
was as follows.
If we're going to scale up data,
we're going to have a bunch of people
collecting data. Those people might have
different ways of solving problems and
so there'll be multiple strategies for
solving problems represented in our data
set. For example, if we have an
obstacle, we might have trajectories
that go above the obstacle or go below
the obstacle or left or right. And these
will result in multiple modes in the
data that we collect.
So as a consequence of this, the
distribution of the actions we expect to
see should have multiple modes that we
observe.
Right? So why don't we train policies
that are capable of representing the
multiple modes that we see in the action
distribution? Right? So training
policies that can fit these kinds of
functions.
So there are a bunch of models that that
came out just pri- previously to this
work, like the diffusion model, which
were able to do this for images. And so
around 2023, some some work like the
diffusion policy from from from Chong
Jie formerly Columbia, now at Sanctuary
Robotics,
sort of said, "Okay, well, why don't we
just use these like imitative generative
models as a way of parameterizing action
distributions so I can represent these
complex action distributions over here."
So today, generative control policies
are the basis for the majority of robot
VLA models. These are not the kind of
newest, fanciest, shiniest things that
use VideoGen, though even those are
using generative models as well.
Uh and theoretically, GCPs are are are
very powerful, right? They can actually
imitate arbitrary stochastic expert
demonstrations and if you use a little
bit of low-level control, you can also
make them do so stably.
So to stress, like generative control, I
think from a public point of view, is is
kind of considered one of the
technologies that's that's that's
regarded for like the revolution in
robot capabilities. It's suddenly things
change when we started using generative
models.
And even kind of the most frontier VLAs
still are using something like a
flow-based model to do this prediction.
So what do you do with a generative
model or generative control policy?
Well, you just take your loss function
in behavior cloning and you replace it
with a distribution fitting objective.
So for example, you can use the flow
matching objective. I'm sure many of us
are familiar with this. Essentially,
what flow matching does is it learns to
interpolate between actions and pure
noise and it learns the velocity or the
average velocity velocity between the
line between them, which is just going
to be given by the difference between
the noise and the action.
And you fit this velocity field and then
if you want to generate an action, you
initialize the initialize the action as
pure Gaussian noise and then you evolve
the ODE back in time. This would
probably be a negative sign giving you
an action because you're learning this
velocity field which defines an ODE.
So, the main question we're going to try
to ask is, are these generative control
policies are they really about
distribution matching? Or are they
giving us something else? And maybe
giving us something else that's related
to some of the control perspective that
we've described described earlier. So,
that's what I'm going to try to argue.
So, in order to understand what
generative control policies are giving
us, it's useful to kind of disambiguate
the different design decisions that go
into a generative control policy.
So, we came up with a taxonomy that
includes three of them. The first is the
one that's most visible, the one that
they were motivated for, which is
distributional learning. A flow model, a
diffusion model can validly approximate
any conditional distribution if your
neural network is big enough, if you've
got enough data.
Right? So, that's where this
multimodality that we care about.
Now, the second is uh stochasticity.
When we train a a generative model, most
of the very popular ones include a
little bit of Gaussian noise in the way
that they're trained, and you might
think that this improves training
dynamics, it improves representation
learning, it functions as data
augmentation. And so, maybe the use of
stochasticity is the thing that's really
important here.
And then last thing is that is this idea
of iterative computation, right? So,
we've seen in language models, for
example, that chain of thought, multiple
steps are are really useful for
representing more complicated outputs.
And maybe something else is going on
here as well, something similar is going
on here, right? So, here when we use a
flow model, we take multiple steps by
integrating this ODE, we use Euler
discretization. So, we might have five
or 10 steps to predict an action rather
than predicting in a single step.
Now, in a little bit more detail, what
we actually do in a flow model is called
supervised iterative computation.
Where if we look at the flow matching
loss, it's kind of supervising the
velocity field at every step of this
denoising process. So, every step of
this is being supervised. And so, it's
giving us like dense information around
every step of our kind of like internal
thinking.
So, these are the components. So, let's
try to understand which components
actually matter.
Are generative control policies doing
distribution learning?
So, I want to make a caveat cuz
yesterday Katerina brought up a really
good point. For this talk, we're talking
about reactive control policies. So, you
could also use diffusion for planning,
you could use it for key pose
prediction, you could use it for key
frame prediction. In those cases, you
will probably see a lot of multimodality
because you're predicting things long
into the future. Right? But in this
talk, we're focusing on reactive control
policies, which are rather more near
term.
And for reactive control policies, what
we did is we compared to um between
flow-based policies and regression-based
policies across a range of tasks, from
mostly from simulated environments. Now,
simulation has its weaknesses, but a lot
of these simulations were mainly mainly
the simulations that were claimed as the
reason for why you need generative
control policies. And these include many
conventionally multimodal simulation
tasks. So, what we do is we plot in gray
the performance of a regression policy.
Sorry, it's so faint on this. Maybe this
is not a
uh presentation optimized uh color
scheme. Uh And what we do here this this
gray this red dotted line, this denotes
where the regression policy dips below
95% of the flow-based policy.
So, we see that actually in the
overwhelming majority of tasks with lots
of image modalities, different VLA
backbone states, images, 3D point
clouds, flow-based policies and
regression-based policies are
competitive.
So, why didn't people notice this
before?
Well, one important thing is you need to
control for architecture. So, it turns
out the diffusion transformer with its
outer layer norm is also a wonderful way
to train a regression model. But uh in
the original papers,
they bladed an MLP with regression
against a transformer with something
else. People hadn't done other forms of
transformer architectures for
regression, but not the specific kind of
bells and whistles that were used in
diffusion, and these seem to work very
well.
Um but it's still the case that there
are many tasks on this this this handful
over here where flow-based models are
still doing much better. So, let's try
to understand what what they are.
Um So, are the improvements on tasks
that have very explicit multimodality,
explicitly many solutions. Again, this
is reactive control policies and not key
frame prediction. So, our first finding
is that the tasks where it seems that
flow policies do the best are actually
those that require lots of high
precision, things like tool insertion.
Um okay.
The second is, can we look at the tasks
where flow and regression are
competitive, but maybe ask if flow is
still learning to be multimodal in some
way?
So, let's do that. First, what we did is
we visualize the action distributions
either on the in the image space or with
like a UMAP embedding. And we even color
coded the actions by their return to go,
so how good the action is. And what we
see is no perceptible multimodality. And
in fact, we also don't even see that
there's any really any real pattern
between how good the action is and where
the action lies in the visualization.
Now, of course, there are limitations to
these visualization tools, but at least
perceptibly, there's no multimodality.
But of course, like there's so many
limitations with visualization alone, so
we need another experiment.
So, what we did here is we took three
ways of doing inference on the control
policy. That's uh so, flow policy, it
takes initial Gaussian noise, it maps it
by integrating an ODE to an action.
So, you can either take the initial
noise to be Gaussian.
You can set the initial noise to be
zero. Or you could do something that
will explicitly destroy the
multimodality. You can sample 64 noise
seeds, take all the actions that you get
from those noises, and just average them
together. So, effectively, you're
approximating this distribution with its
mean.
Right? So, this destroys any
multimodality, and what we find is if
you do this, you lose a bit of
performance, but you only lose 2%
performance.
Very, very little. So, at least the
representation of multimodality in these
policies does not seem to be
particularly helpful, right? You can
basically destroy it, and and they work
pretty well.
Now, the final question is, what happens
if you try to relabel the data so that
the data is deterministic and high
quality?
So, if you relabel your data so it's
higher quality, you actually do see a
slight narrowing of the gap between a
flow and a regression model, right? They
regression does get better, flow gets
worse depending on how we did the
relabeling.
Uh but you still see this gap, right?
So, even from deterministic data, it
seems that there's some benefit to flow
over regression.
So, what's going on?
Well, at least we can say that in the
tasks that we're studying,
distributional learning is not the main
component. I think when you move to the
pretraining scale, it certainly is, and
I still think that you should pretrain
the flow policy, so don't get me wrong.
I think the point of this talk is more
to understand other mechanisms that flow
policies might be doing that are
underappreciated.
So, what we're going to try to do to
understand what factors are contributing
to flow success, is we're going to try
to design an algorithm as an ablation.
So, we're going to try to design an an
algorithm which does not correctly
approximate distributions, but which
exhibits the stochasticity and the
supervised iterative computation that
are observed in flow models. And if
these things do as well, that kind of
gives us evidence that these two
components are really the salient
factors.
So, that policy is very simple. Uh the
policy first does regression to predict
an action.
And then what we do is we add a little
bit of noise to our action.
And then we do another step of
regression to predict the action again.
Right? So, we kind of tell the policy
how to correct its own actions.
So, if you want to do inference on this
policy, what you do is you just first
predict your original action, and then
you can choose to add noise, you don't
have to, but you just set feed that
action back to the second stage policy,
and use that to design a correction. And
that's your final action.
So, this policy is very um uses
iterative computation in a very minimal
way, so we called it MIP, the minimal
iterative policy.
And this is kind of as an ablation to
investigate what flow is really giving
us.
So, these two things.
So, what did what what how does MIP do?
Well, it turns out that among the tasks
where uh flow models do better than
regression, MIP performs competitively
with if not sometimes better than flow
models across all these tasks.
So, this suggests that this sort of
component two and component three,
stochasticity and supervised iterative
computation, benefit you. However, if
you only use component two or component
three in isolation, not combined, they
don't work. So, if you don't have
stochasticity, intuitively, uh it's hard
to like learn the self-corrections
because you're not giving your your
second action enough coverage, so that
sort of breaks down. And if you only
have component three, then you're not
really benefiting anything, your neural
network learns to ignore the noise if
you have no iterative computation and
just extra noise.
So, you need to kind of combine the two.
So, now you can we're trying to
understand, well, what are the benefits?
Where is this iterative computation
helping us?
So, let me give a sort of a mental
picture for how you might think this is
useful.
So, um suppose that you're training, and
you have demonstrations that are sparse,
they're they're they're they're
suspended in high-dimensional space.
So, you could think that your policy
learns multimodality. It says, "Oh,
well, I have these two strategies, maybe
sometime I'll go left, sometimes I'll go
right." That's B2.
But our experiment suggests that we
don't we're not really learning
multimodality, not at least at this
scale.
So, another thing that we could learn
instead of multimodality is rapid
switching. So, we could say, "Oh, well,
if I'm on the left slightly, I always go
left. If I'm on the right slightly, I'll
always go right." So, I'll learn a
policy that changes very rapidly, and
that's called having a high Lipschitz
constant.
So, maybe the the supervised
computation, the iterative computation
helps represent this really fast change,
this high Lipschitz constant, right? So,
why would we believe this? Well, we know
that deep neural networks are much
better at representing high Lipschitz
functions than shallow neural networks.
And we can also think about our
iterative steps of computation as kind
of functioning like a deeper neural
network, right? If you have more steps
to go, it's kind of like you have more
layers in your network, sort of, right?
That was at least our first belief.
But it turns out that's wrong.
So, that you can actually show that if
you're not learning multimodality, you
can't represent more complex functions
by using more multiple steps of
computation, at least naively. Uh it
just doesn't benefit you. Uh the reason
being that in the absence of
multimodality, kind of your flow always
kind of converges back to this kind of
like connected distribution, and you
don't really have any ability to sort of
shift that more rapidly than you would
with just pure regression.
So, what is happening? So, let me give a
tangent that's related to control, and
use that to contextualize what's going
on.
Imagine that rather than getting expert
data, we try to collect exploratory
data. And this better data collection is
is is sort of essential in sort of all
of robotics, in particular in behavior
cloning. So, let's consider a stylized
example, it's based off
on the DART algorithm from Kevin Laskey
and others. So, what we're going to do
is we're just going to collect data by
adding noise to our actions, like some
small amount of noise to our actions.
Now, when we get that that that those
states, we're going to take expert uh
we're going to collect the expert
actions at those states. So, these are
noisy states that we get to or states
that are achieved by noisy exploration,
they give us expert actions that we
should take.
And now, what we're going to do is train
a policy that imitates the clean expert
actions, but does so under the
distribution of noisy states, right? So,
the noisy states just give us
exploration, the imitation is to clean
actions.
Okay. So, it looks something like this,
right? We're trying to imitate uh the
red's trying to imitate the light blue.
So, what you can show is that if you do
this scheme,
even if the system is open-loop
unstable,
you will always be able to imitate
without compounding error.
So, just this little bit of perturbation
to the to the actions is able to
overcome the lower bound and actually
always give you imitation learning
guarantees.
And in fact, kind of what's sort of
miraculous about this is that you kind
of magically find the states or the the
directions in state space that are most
susceptible to compounding error. So,
because your expert is adding noise to
dynamical system, even if the expert
keeps everything stable, it's sort of
exploring every direction that could go
unstable under learning, which is kind
of magical. Okay.
So, we're not going to do this. In fact,
just adding noise to your actions might
be a very bad idea depending on the
hardware that you have.
But, we're going to argue that maybe
flow models are doing a little bit of
this or doing something somewhat
equivalent to this.
Okay.
So, let me explain how we did this. So,
what we're going to what we're going to
do is we're going to take a flow model
and we're going to look at what it does
on states that we reach via this noisy
data collection.
So, imagine here you have your actions
and states, you get some expert action,
and you make some prediction, that's
your flow prediction.
So, now, what we're going to do is we're
going to imagine the other actions that
we would have achieved. And these other
actions that we would have achieved are
ones that we would get to if we just
perturb previous actions. So, we're kind
of exploring through the system and then
we're looking getting to slightly
different states and we're looking at
the actions at those different states.
And so, we'll just take the stay on the
vector space that's spanned by all these
actions and we'll call this the
localized action manifold.
Okay.
So, now, for every action that we
predict, you can think about two sources
of error.
You can think of the source of error
that that says you were on the right
manifold, but you maybe made a mistake,
or the source of error which is your
orthogonal to the manifold, you're off
the manifold.
And we plot these two.
And what we see is that flow models,
they don't have better validation losses
naively. So, they're making the same
amount of error,
but the location of that error seems to
be uh less off the manifold and more on
the manifold. So, I'll give you like a
visual description. Imagine I need to do
an insertion task, right? On the
manifold is this way. If I go faster or
slower, I still insert the the tool.
But, if I go off the manifold, I miss.
And it seems that flow models seem to
have this inductive bias that seems to
be very useful in robotics. And so,
they're they're kind of like trained
towards learning this like local action
manifold that we get from noising. And
the noising would be the thing that if
we imitated perfectly under that
distribution, we would actually have no
compounding error. So, it's not exactly
like we're doing getting data for free,
we're just using an inductive bias
that's very beneficial.
Right.
So, the way that we kind of think about
this is that at every step of the
computation, the flow model is trying to
come up with an action, and the
correction step is sort of smoothing
both in because it's conditioned both on
observation and its own noisy action,
it's smoothing both in observation and
action space. And by smoothing in both,
we still don't really fully understand
how this works, but we just have
evidence that this is happening. It's
actually quite hard to prove that this
works. Uh but, what we it seems to be
going on is that you're getting this
inductive bias towards this off this on
manifold error, and this is predictive
of increased performance.
So, essentially, these two ingredients,
stochasticity and iterative computation,
they're inducing this inductive bias,
they're inducing they're sort of putting
your error in in the directions where
sort of it's it's unavoidable to make
error, but if you make error in those
directions, you're not suffering too
much.
And so, I kind of our takeaway is that a
big part of the benefit of generative
control policies is actually their
benefits for the control, not just their
benefits for distribution learning from
from modality matching.
Um for those of you that are interested
in using MIP, uh we're at CMU, so I
would just say email Chui if you if
you're curious about it. Uh but, the
kind of TLDR is is it does work with
VLAs in certain cases.
Uh it actually does preserve task
diversity. So, here's a fun thing about
reactive control policies, even
regression policies can be multimodal at
the level of trajectories.
Sort of the mental model you should have
is that yes, you might have some
unimodal distribution, but as you keep
running and re- re- running your policy
from those modes, you can still get
branching as you run it keep running it
over and over.
Um
Right. So, that still preserves task
diversity.
Um however, I would say don't use MIP
unless you need need to. So, it's really
good for ablations, and if you need fast
inference, we find that it works better
than consistency-based models.
Uh however, if you want to do things
that are pre-training scale, for
example, or if you want to do video
prediction, long horizon prediction, key
frame pose prediction, there is
multimodality and do not use MIP. Uh
also, for reinforcement learning, uh
flow-based models just work way way
better. That's a whole different reason.
Um and I can talk to you guys offline
about why that's the case.
Um okay, one other cool point before we
wrap up is that uh there's one kind of
maybe interesting property about flow
models, which is what they do about
uncertainty. So, imagine that I have a
function that's really really hard to
fit, like y = sin(1/x).
So, if I try to fit it with a regression
model, I'm going to oversmooth in the
middle cuz I can't fit it. If I try to
fit it with a flow model and I only use
one noise vector, uh I'm also going to
oversmooth in maybe a slightly different
way.
But, now, if I aggregate and average
over all my noise samples, I'm going to
take this part of the function that's
super hard to fit, and I'm actually
instead going to learn some noisy thing.
I'm going to learn some distribution.
So, one way to interpret what's going on
here is that you have high local
epistemic uncertainty. You don't really
know what's going on here, it's very
hard to fit it.
And that a flow model can kind of
convert this into aleatoric uncertainty
into variance over its prediction. And
so, I've been working with a couple
students at MIT on kind of understanding
how generalizable this phenomena is.
So, maybe let's conclude. Uh sort of in
this talk, we tried to take a
control-theoretic perspective showing
that uh continuous control can be
fundamentally more challenging than
learning in the in the uh discrete
world.
Um the we tried to argue that the
inflection point witnessed in robotics
arose because in it the interventions
that we developed inadvertently
addressed these control-theoretic
challenges that we encountered. For
example, action chunking allowed us to
learn stably in in in open-loop stable
systems, and generative control sort of
behaves in some ways like what we might
get from better data augmentation
without doing it explicitly.
So, kind of this is sort of the evidence
of this algorithmic Moravec's paradox
view that robot learning is
fundamentally harder unless you do a
couple of things that might be somewhat
non-obvious.
So, I want to maybe end with what I what
what remains hard about robotics. And
there there two maybe different views,
right? So, one is maybe nothing once we
get enough data.
Um this is kind of like the antithesis
of Moravec's paradox. And sort of one
thing that I think about, maybe it's
useful for students as well, is that
there's this unfortunate tension between
like how useful a task is and how hard
it is to learn. So, tasks that are very
useful also show up a lot in our economy
or we're willing to spend money
collecting data. So, even if there's a
more elegant solution, there's always
someone who's willing to pay you to data
collect. And unfortunately, this results
in this kind of inverse correlation
where a lot of the tasks that we really
want to solve as academics lie here
where they're really hard because we
don't have a lot of data, but often
times it's hard to convince people to
pay you to get it's hard to convince
people that that's sort of economically
viable. And the tasks that have a lot of
impact, you can just kind of MTurk your
way out of them. Uh so, that's sort of
my bitter lesson. But, I actually think
that there are really fundamental
challenges in the longer horizon, and I
think the main challenge I think lots of
us agree is that we don't have any model
that goes and adapts and learns sort of
on its own, right? So, my favorite
example is that orangutans can drive.
Right? Uh they drive really well, and
the amount of training flops needed to
learn to drive is probably pretty small.
Uh I especially if you compare to Waymo.
>> [laughter]
>> So, I think that we still have a ways to
go, but maybe it's less about
capabilities and more about these kind
of meta capabilities.
Um and then lastly, I want to end with
like a little coda about what's what
might what we might learn about this
going sort of beyond robotics. So,
compounding error can arise in any
situation where you have a model that's
deployed in closed loop with itself. So,
that could be language modeling as you
generate your own outputs, that could be
generative modeling as you have a flow
of many steps.
And we might ask ourselves if there are
some deep learning optimizations that
might directly attack this compounding
error even without new data, much in the
way that flow models give us better
generalization without explicitly
collecting more new data.
So, this is kind of useful in this kind
of tail case, right?
So, uh one Thomas who the action
chunking work has been sort of working
on an optimizer also with my student
Efe, um which can show improvements in
not necessarily training curves, but in
terms of actual generalization error
when deployed on robotics, but also in
cases of language and in fact in
generative modeling. And it suggests
that there's still like a whole world of
deep learning principles to be explored
to investigate this test time feedback.
Uh and please expect an archive release
of that soon in the next few weeks, and
thanks for coming.
>> [applause]
>> Cool. Questions?
Yes, Stephen. I thought of a question in
the reverse order. So, Yeah. first
generalization, the very last
generalization that you mentioned about
like noising the expert, you can't
actually train that, is that right?
Because you would need to like noise and
then get expert demonstrations if you
like Oh, yeah, you have to change how
your data your data's actually
collected. Yeah. Yes, exactly. So, I
mean, you can train that, you just
assume that your expert controls the
data differently. So, in practice, what
people will do is they won't noise their
actions, but they'll kind of have an
expert collect for coverage data,
they'll have an expert show some
mistakes and how to fix those mistakes,
and that seems to be very empirically
useful.
Yeah. And then for the MIP, I think the
equations were a bit wrong, so I didn't
parse them too well, but like the
first one, you you train one on just
pure regression? Yeah. And then you
noise it, and then you
and then Yes. Okay.
Yeah. You and and then you made a maybe
offhand remark about how the flow is
both noising actions and observations?
Uh no, not exactly. The flow is noising
actions, but the point is that the flow
is recovering certain inductive biases
that you might have gotten if you were
noising the observations. And the like
the 15 In the manifold thing, yeah,
exactly.
And then for the like evaluations, you
mentioned that like action chunking
it's the like roll evaluation length
that matters and not just the chunk
length. Well, it's the evaluation
length, not just the training length,
right? Because if you want to predict a
chunk of say 16, you have to train to
predict at least 16 steps, and then you
can evaluate up to 16 steps. So, if it
was just a representation learning
effect, then you might be able to train
predicting 16 steps and roll out one
step at a time. But, in fact, you need
to roll out 4 8 16 to reap the benefits.
Yeah. So, so in in language models, when
you do auto regression, like it's
non-Markovian because you're training on
a pre-like a previous tokens, but you
are rolling it out one by one. Yeah,
Markovian is complicated. If the context
is state, then it is Markovian.
We can talk about that offline because I
want to let's have Yeah. Thanks,
Stephen.
Yes. What's the name of your work again
that talked about this off-manifold and
on-manifold error between regression and
Uh much ado about noising. Much ado
about noising, yeah. Yeah.
Yes.
You mentioned that in the long term we
might not need action chunking and I
think there's a lot of cases where you
need like really high frequency control
like in contact.
Um
can you talk a little bit more about
what innovations need to
>> Yeah. Yeah, so I think that the right
way to do this is you can predict long
sequence um
there are students in the room who are
working with me on sort of the next
version of this, but you can you
basically should have some form of
predicting long sequence things for
consistency, but then if you want high
precision control uh all of my negative
results go away if you move from an act
from a behavior cloning paradigm to like
a reinforce online reinforcement
learning paradigm. So, reinforcement
learning sucks at exploration at least
previous currently, but if your action
chunking seed or if your behavior
cloning seeds it into like a good kind
of warm start, it's very easy to learn
how to improve your control policy with
on-policy reinforcement learning. And
so, I think we're going to use that to
learn to learn sort of high frequency
residuals, for example. Yeah. So, is
that online reinforcement learning
process actually solving the issue of
like the compounding error?
>> Yes, it can. Exactly. Because one way to
think about it is the online
reinforcement learning gives you a
little bit of that exploration. And that
exploration kind of gives you that those
directions that might be unstable, and
then it just teaches you how to kind of
correct from those. Yeah.
Yes. For action chunking, how big is K
star compared to the horizon?
>> the the the the answer is four or eight.
The second that's like the So, it
actually depends. If you're using it for
pre-training, a lot of pre-trained
models will use very long action chunks
because they are probably also using it
for representation learning and for very
complicated tasks. So, I think Pi uses
like 50 I I believe, but um in sort of
like these more simulation and
experiments, typically four or eight is
like the standard. So, if you were to
pull up your favorite like diffusion RL
in robotics paper, it'd be around four
or eight. Yeah.
Cool.
Yes. A quick follow-up point. So, so you
said that K star depends on all these
like properties of like the dynamics and
etc. etc. Like do you have a way of
estimating K star predictively or do you
just kind of
do a sweep on K star and be like which
one actually works? I think I think in
practice, I mean the the the sad thing
about theory is that theory can give you
qualitative insights, but it's like I'm
not it's hard to get bounds that are
tight and predictive. Uh so, I think in
practice, you your grad student tries
four or eight.
>> [laughter]
>> And I'm sorry.
I want to be honest about that, but I
think that's that's what ends up
happening. It's is it's like uh yeah.
Uh um
probably any bound that you would derive
theoretically would be overly
pessimistic as these kind of bounds are.
Yeah.
Yes.
In language models, there is a like a
compression trick for long context
generation where as you generate, you
are like compressing the
uh like key value caches in Yes. the
prefix. And I'm trying I'm wondering
whether there is a connection between
this compression trick and the
stability.
For example, like whether this
compression is destroying stability or
improving stability. That's a great
question. I actually think it's
improving stability. So, the thing with
a language model is that it's a really
complicated dynamical system because as
you add more context, your Think of the
think of the dynamical system not just
as your language model, but as every
layer in the language model. So, like
you kind of have this two-level thing
where like your language model creates
this like a layer makes a step, a layer
makes a step, a layer makes a step.
You're done with the forward pass, you
put you write a token, and step steps
up, right? So, the more you have in
context, basically like the wider range
of things that your attention has to pay
attention to. And this can cause various
forms of like attention glitches. Like
there've been a lot of papers I think
2022 like Bing Bin Lu wrote some really
nice papers on this. And so, one way to
interpret this compression is just
saying that like a lot of weird sort of
like erratic errors in like your
attention weights where things weren't
learned perfectly, those can add up a
ton uh in the in in history, and if you
don't do compression, then uh then you
might like pay attention to a lot of
these spurious things that add up and
have a like sort of play a larger role
in the attention weight. Yeah.
Thank you. Yeah, of course.
Cool. Yeah. Uh you mentioned in one of
the slides you are comparing the
continuous and discrete learning
paradigms.
Uh I know there's like pushes recently
to frame robotics as like discrete
learning. Uh do you think all of these
innovations will still hold any
important if we learn robotics as a
discrete problem? So, I've been thinking
a lot about this because I've been
talking to some people who want to
rethink kind of how to do tokenization
in robotics.
The the my current stance on this is
that if you wanted turn everything into
discrete tokens,
I don't know how you onboard new tokens,
right? So, imagine that like all my
robots are trained to be normal and then
they start like doing this, but it's
like for an interpretive dance and they
have to, right? Like how does my
tokenizer add that to the tokens? I
don't really know. So, there's also
issues with precision. So, I currently
think that it's very useful to still
have continuous, but to think of these
as decoders or renderers rather than
think of them as learners. So, that you
can still pre-train on everything as
being kind of continuous, but you can
you can you can Yeah. I think but I I
and so like I think in principle you
could represent everything in discrete.
Uh but you what people don't people
don't want just to like discretize
actions, they want actually tokenize
actions into meaningful hierarchical
structure and compress actions. I think
that's the issue. I think ultimately
1e-4%
is probably enough. I don't think humans
have much better than that. So, we could
just like, you know, do like a whatever
like exponent and mantissa thing in in
robotics and that would be fine. But, I
think like deeper like actually
compression compressing action spaces
probably should be combined with sort of
a decoder. The one fun fact, humans are
also discrete. I think the way that our
our motor system works from what I
understand, we have like some number of
motor units and they fire either by in a
binary fashion. So, we are kind of using
like discrete things, but we're not
we're not compressed, right? Like those
motor units are independent and there
are millions of them or some number of
them, right? They're not the kind of
like four or eight sequence tokens that
people are hoping to find.
Cool.
All right, with that let's say thank YOU
ONCE AGAIN.
>> [applause]
>> THANK YOU, EVERYONE. WE'LL SEE YOU NEXT
WEEK.
>> THANKS.